French Literature mss., LMC 1391 LMC 1391
Lilly Library
- French Literature mss.
  - Gourmont, Remy de, 1858-1915, critic. 122 rue de Sac, Paris. To Octave Henri Marie Mirbeau. Writes of sending him the three copies of "Phocas" and discusses problems he's been having Xan, and the Conseil d'Administration. A.L.S., 1894 Dec 5; 4 p. 22 cm.
    Removed from Remy de Gourmont, Phocas, Paris: L'Ymagier, 1895 (Lilly PQ2266 .P574 3 copies) which is dedicated to Mirbeau. 1977
  - Maurras, Charles Marie Photius, 1868-1952, critic, author. 19, rue du Dragon, Paris. To "monsieur et cher confrère". Thanks him for the complimentary article he wrote concerning Maurras's book. A.L.S., 1895 Apr 20; [2] p. 21 cm.
    Removed from Maurras, Le chemin de paradis. Paris: C. Lévy, 1895 (Lilly PQ2625 .A954 C52). 1981
  - Goudeau, Emile, 1849-1906, writer. Bibliophilie and Notes Cyclistes, [poems]., 1896 Apr.; 4 p. 20.5 cm.
    Removed from Goudeau, Poemes Parisiens. Paris: H. Beraldi, 1897 (Lilly PQ2265.G64 P74). 1980
  - Barbusse, Henri, 1847-1935, author. Paris. To Alexandre Louis Marie Charpentier. Expresses his appreciation for the work done by Charpentier on the occasion of Barbusse's betrothal to the daugther of "votre ami Mendès." A.L.S., 1897 Jul 25; 2 p. 18 cm.
    Paper is watermarked Paris Louvre Superieur.
  - Lorrain, Jean, 1855-1906. To Voirot, Sebastien. A.L.S., 1897 Nov.; 1 p. 14 cm.
    Removed from Lorrain, Jean, Theatre... Paris: Société d'éditions littéraires et artistiques: Librairie Paul Ollendorff, 1906 (Lilly PQ2235.D93 T37) 2004
  - Leconte, Sebastién Charles, 1865-1934, poet. Les Bijoux de Marguerite. A.D., 1899?; [102] leaves 32 cm.
    Printer's copy in ink written in cursive and printed styles.
    Has 165 numbered leaves with blank leaves noted on preceding pages; leaf 163/4 may be missing.
    Some poems with corrections.
    Watermark: L.JDL&Cie.
    Published in Paris, Edition du Mercure de France, 1899.
    Formerly in the collection of Jules Marsan.
    Purchase. 1980
  - Banville, Théodore de, 1823-1891, author. To "cher ami". Has "un rendez-vous indispensable demain soir." A.L.S., 19th cent.; 2 p. 15.2 cm.
    Removed from Banville, Gringoire: Comédie en un acte en prose. Paris: Michel Lévy Frères, 1866 (Lilly PQ2187 .G86) 1994
  - Barbier, Auguste, 1805-1882. "Melodie" and "Dernier soupir du Boston", poems., 19th cent.; 2 p. 20.5 cm.
    Removed from Auguste Barbier, Iambes. Paris: Urbain Canel et Ad. Guyot, 1832 (Lilly PQ2189 .B33 1832) 1985
  - Jammes, Francis, 1868-1938, poet, novelist. Orthez, France. To Van Mous. Writes concerning a visit of his friend's children and compares his solitude with the charm of family life. A.L.S., 1900 Apr 28; 2 p. 29 cm.
  - Zola, Emile, 1840-1902, author. Paris. To Monsieur. Offers praise for "la Société la Croix-Rouge." A.L.S., 1900 Oct 5; 2 p. 20 cm.
    Purchase. 1967
  - Toulet, Paul Jean, 1867-1920, author. To Madame Prieu. 2 place La Fayette, Bagneres de Bigorre, [France]. With the best wishes of Paul to all the family. A.P.S., 1903 Apr 2; 9 cm
    Postcard picturing Village au Kinh-Luoc Pagode des Roses.
    Removed from Paul Jean Toulet, La jeune fille verte, Paris: Emile-Paul Frères, 1920 (Lilly PQ2639 .O88J54). 1977
  - Claudel, Paul Louis Charles Marie, 1868-1955, diplomat, poet, dramatist. Les Choephous. A.D., 1905 Mar 25; 2 p. 32 cm.
    Note in another hand states the page was written by Claudel on this date.
    Discussion of the second work, Choephoroe, of the Orestian trilogy by Aeschylus.
    Removed from Chaudel, L'Announce faite à Marie, Paris, Editions de la Nouvelle Revue François, 1912 (Lilly PQ2605 .L2A85). 1974
  - Maurras, Charles Marie Photius, 1868-1952, critic, author. To "monsieur et cher confrère." Extends thanks and congratulations. Understands that he is back from Spain: will send a copy of his last book. A.L.S., 1905 Nov 1; 1 p. 21 cm.
    Removed from Maurras, L'avenir de l'intelligence. Paris: A. Fontemoing, 1905 (Lilly PQ2625 .A954 A94). 1981
  - Meunier, Charles, 1866-1940, bookbinder. To Mon cher ami. Concerned with bookbinding and "Amis de Livres." A.L.S., 1905 Apr 11; 2 p. 18 cm.
    Identification is tentative; signed with the last name.
    Paper watermarked Verge Blanc Créme Superieur and Au Bon Marché Loyaute surround a seated figure.
    Removed from Joris Karl Huysmans, Le qvartier Notre Dame. Paris, Librairie de la Collection des Dix, A. Romagnol, 1905 (Lilly PQ2309 .H4).
    Volume was bound by Meunier and bears the signature of Romagnol.
    Accessioned in Mss. Dept. in 1974
  - Proust, Marcel, 1871-1922, author. To Fernand Gregh. Comments on some of his own works, nationalism, and mentions Paul Dubois. A.L.S., 1905 June.; [10] p. 17.5 cm.
    Watermark: Au Printemps Paris Nouveau Papier Français.
    Date derived from date assigned for the publication of the letter in Correspondence de Marcel Proust, text…par Philip Kolb, Paris, Plon, 1979 (Main Library PQ2631 .R8Z4245), vol. 5, pages 273-279.
    Letter does not bear the initials M.P. at its end which are given on page 276 of the published work.
    Removed from Gregh, L'or des minutes: poésies. Paris, Bibliotheque-Charpentier, 1905 (Lilly PQ2613 .R4063). 1984
  - Berger, Philippe, 1846-1912, scholar. To "Monsieur et honoré collegue." M. Fossey. A.L.S., 1906 Jan 15; 3 p. 18 cm.
    Removed from Berger's Histoire de l'ecriture dans l'aniquite… Paris, Imprimerie nationale, 1891 (Lilly P211 .B5). 1965
  - Brunetiére, Ferdinand, 1849-1906, editor. Revue des Deux-Mondes, 15, Rue de L'Université, Paris. To [Marcel Prévost]. Writes that he is enclosing with letter a check for 18,000F to settle the balance on publishing Monsieur et Madame Moloch. Postscripts mentions he will be found in office next Wednesday, Oct. 31. A.L.S., 1906 Oct 27; 2 p. 18 cm.
    Enclosure is not present.
    Removed from Prevost, Monsieur et Madame Moloch. Paris: Alphonse Lemmerre, 1906 (Lilly PQ2383 .P6M75). 1977
  - Philippe, Charles Louis, 1874-1909, novelist. Cérilly (Allier), [France]. To [?]. Is vacationing and asks that he send the latest issue of "Ermitage". Hopes to see him in October. A.L.S., 1906 Sept. 19; 1 p. 21.2 cm.
    Removed from Philippe, Croquignole. Paris: E. Fasquelle, 1906 (Lilly PQ2631 .H5 C94). 1981
  - Tharaud, Jerome, 1874-1953, novelist, essayist. 17 Quai Voltaire, Paris. To Monsieur. Confirms an engagement. A.L.S., 1907 Jan 18; 1 p. 18 cm.
    Signed J.J. Tharaud, the signature adopted by the two brothers, Jerome and Jean (1877-1952) Tharaud, when writing a common letter.
    Mounted in Jerome and Jean Tharaud, L'Ombre de la Croix. Paris, Emile-Paul, 1917 (Lilly PQ2639.H13 O5 1917). 1959
  - Delisle, Leopold Victor, 1826-1910, author. To "Mon cher confrère, collegue & ami." Refers to some publications of the Académie des inscriptions et belles-lettres. A.L.S., 1907 Dec 12; 1 p. 18 cm.
    Removed from Delisle's Recherches sur la Librairie de Charles V (Extrait) Hommage a l'Académie des inscriptioins et belles-lettres, 1857-1907. Paris, 1907. (Lilly AS162 .P315) From the library of Coella Lindsay Ricketts, Chicago, Illinois. 1967
  - Lanson, Gustave?, 1857-1934, author. To Edouard Jean Marie Champion. Does not wish to be a candidate for academy; praises work of Sturel. A.L.S., 1908 May 12; 2 p. 17 cm.
    Removed from Charles Louis de Secondat, baron de La Brède et de Montesquieu, ... Montesquietu, Textes Choisis et Commentés par Fortunat Strowski. Paris, 1912. (PQ2011 .A17S9). 1951
  - Strowski, Fortunat Joseph, 1866-1952, author. Bordeaux, France. To Edouard Jean Marie Champion?. Volume 2 of Montaigne and Volume 3 of Pascal almost finished; volume 3 of Montaigne will be quickly done; religious opinions; mention of works of literary criticism. A.L.S., 1908 Jun 1; 4 p. 15 cm.
    Removed from Charles Louis de Secondat, baron de La Brède et de Montesquieu, ... Montesquieu, Textes Choisis et Commentés par Fortunat Strowski. Paris, 1912. (PQ2011 .A17S9). 1951
  - Henry Fernard, 1859-, translator. To [Jean Adrien Antoine Jules Jusserand] Asking permission to dedicate his translation of John Milton's Les Petits Poémes… to him. A.L.S., 1909 Feb 23; 4 p. 19 cm.
    Mounted on front flyleaf of John Milton's Les Petits Poémes… Traduits… Par Fernand Henry… Paris, Libraire Orientale & Américaine, 1909. (Lilly PR3554.F5 H4) 1961
  - Bergson, Henri Louis, 1859-1941, philosopher. Villa Montmorency, 18 Avenue des Villeurs, Montmorency, France. To Mon cher ami. Writes of profiting from the leave of absence from Peguy and argues that this friend has criticised George Sand, whom he admired in his youth, too severely. A.L.S., 1909 Apr 21; 3 p. 15 cm.
    Removed from Henri Louis Bergson, L'Énergie spirituelle: essais et conférences, Paris: Libraire Félix Alcan, 1919 (Lilly B2430 .B4 E47). 1977
  - Boissy, d'Anglas, François Antoine, 1846-1921, baron, senator. Sénat. To Albert Auguste Gabriel Hanotaux. L'Academie francaise Anciens Ministre des Affaires Étrangères. Asks for help concerning the problem of the identity of the son of Louis XVII and what happened to him. A.L.S., 1909 May 16; 4 p. 23 cm.
    Removed from François Antoine Boissy d'Anglas, Louis XVII et ses descendants, au gouvernement de la republique française, Annonay: Elie Cellier (Lilly DC137.3 .B864). 1977
  - Henry, Fernand, 1859-, translator. Riez, Basses-Alpes, France. To Jean Adrien Antoine Jules Jusserand. Is sending a copy of his translation of John Milton's Les Petits Poémes… A.L.S., 1909 Jun 16; 3 p. 17 cm.
    Mounted on front flyleaf of John Milton's Les Petits Poémes… Traduits… par Fernand Henry… Paris, Libraire Orientale & Américaine, 1909. (Lilly PR3554.F5 H4) 1961
  - Larbaud, Valéry, 1881-1957, poet. 44 Dover Street, Piccadilly, London, England. To Dear Sir. Having been introduced to the recipient by D.S. O'Connor, the writer wishes an introduction to Stephen Wheeler who has written about Landor. Larbaud is about to begin his own book on Landor. A.L.S., 1909 Aug 31; 2 p. 18 cm.
  - Strowski, Fortunat Joseph, 1866-1952, author. Bordeaux, France. To Edouard Jean Marie Champion, Paris. Awaiting a position at the Sorbonne; "our book" not forgotten but must get rid of Montaigne and the Bibliothèque française. A. Postcard S., 1910 Nov 27
    Removed from Charles Louis de Secondat, baron de La Brède et de Montesquieu, … Montesquieu, Textes Choisis et Commentés par Fortunat Strowski. Paris, 1912. (PQ2011 .A17S9). 1951
  - Barrès, Maurice, 1862-1923, writer, politician. Chambre des Députés. To Pierre Varenne. Letter of apology. A.L.S., 1911 Jun 4; 2 p. 18 cm.
    In blue ink.
    Addressee pencilled in.
    Removed from Barrès, Le Jardin de Bérénice, Paris, Librairie Academique Didier, Perrin et Cie, 1891 (Lilly PQ2603 .A7J32). 1974
  - Romains, Jules, 1885-1972, novelist, poet. To Paul Fort. Offers four Odes for Vers et Prose. A.L.S., 1912 Nov 21; 1 p. 13 cm.
  - Carco, Francis, 1886-1958, novelist, poet. 4 rue du Lycée, Nice. To "mon cher confrère". "Mon ami Derieux m'ayant écrit que vous auriez l'occasion de reciter un ou deux de mes poèmes …" A.L.S., 1913 Feb 14; 2 p. 21 cm.
    Removed from Carco, Chansons aigres-douces, Paris, Collection des cinq, 1913 (Lilly PQ2605 .A55C45). 1974
  - Curel, François de, 1854-1928, playwright. Château de Ketzing par Gondrexange, (Lorraine), France. To "cher ami." Accepts his congratulations: compliments him on his own work. Hopes to see him in Paris this week. A.L.S., 1913 Apr 6; [2] p. 17.5 cm.
    Removed from Curel, La fille sauvage. Paris: P.V. Stock, 1902 (Lilly PQ2211 .C8 F4). 1980
  - "adresse à M. Chrétien une brochure, avec prière de la joindre au no 3773 de son catalogue, don't elle est le complément indispensable." A. calling card, 1913 Oct 1; 6 cm.
    In ink on calling card of Lazare Hippolyte Sadi Carnot, 1865-1950?, army officer, man of letters
    Removed from Lazare Hippolyte Sadi Carnot, Lazare Carnot, son emprisonnement sans Louis XVI, Paris: Offert aux amis des livres, 1901 (Lilly DC146 .C28 B41). 1977
  - Morand, Paul, 1888-1976, author, diplomat. L'Enfant de Cent Ans. T(carbon), D.S., 1914; [14] p. 26.5 cm.
    Bound in three-quarter morocco and marbled paper cover.
    Written in London.
    Heavily corrected in black ink, red and lead pencil.
  - Fort, Paul, 1872-1960, poet. Paris, France To Michael Sadleir. Deals with Fort's attempts to continue to publish his Poèmes de France. 3 A.L.S. 1T.L.S., 1915 May 11-1916 Sept 17; 10 p. 17-27 cm.
    Removed from Fort's Choix de Ballades Françaises… Paris, 1913. (Lilly PQ2611 .O78C6). 1963
  - ..., Philippe. To [Francis Carco?]. Postcard with picture of French soldiers on verso., 1916 Mar 18; 1 p. 9 cm.
    Removed from Tristan Dereme, Le Poeme de la pipe et de l'escargot. Paris, Emile-Paul Freres, 1920. (Lilly PQ2607.E56 P73). 1980
  - Claudel, Paul Louis Charles Marie, 1868-1955, diplomat, poet, dramatist. L'Homme et Son Desir: poeme plastique. Exemplaire No. XLVIII, Petropolis, Bresil. A.D., 1917; 7 leaves. 30 cm.
    The seven leaves are hinged together to unfold to a length of 196 cm.
    Enclosed in blue boards with white and gold lining.
    Collage of figures in blue and white, in black and gold on blue by Mrs. Audrey (Bapst) Parr. Music by Darius Milhaud.
    Yale University Library holds number 45 of the 53 manuscript copies of this work: Yale University Gazette, July 1975, page 60.
    Purchase. 1974
  - Barrès, Maurice, 1862-1923, writer, politician. Chambre des Députés, Paris. To Madame la Barrone de Fleury. Letter concerning an appointment. A.L.S., 1919 Jul 7; 1 p. 21 cm.
    Addressee written in another hand in blue pencil.
    Removed from Barres, Colette Baudoch…, Paris, Societe d'Edition et de Publications, Librairie Felix Juven, 1909 (Lilly PQ2603 .A7C6). 1974
  - Jusserand, Jean Adrien Antoine Jules, 1855-1932, author, diplomat. Washington, D.C. To Monsieur le Député. "…Au moment solemnel dans l'historie du monde, vous l'avez exposée en la ville que port le nom de cet autre grand Liberateur, George Washington…" A.D.S., 1919 Aug 24; 1 p. 49 cm. (Foliobox 24)
    Written on vellum, torn into two pieces.
    folio.
    Source unknown. 1973
  - Boylesve, René, 1867-1926, novelist. 27 rue des Vignes, Paris. To "Cher Monsieur." Requests that an article by Gonzague Truc concerning himself be published in his "Revue." Expresses interest in writing something for him and hopes they can discuss it. A.L.S., 1919 Oct 13; 1 p. 27.5 cm.
    Removed from Boylesve, Mlle Cloque: roman. Paris: Éditions de la Revue blanche, 1899 (Lilly PQ203. O9 M19 1899). 1991
  - Grasset, Bernard, 1881-1955, publisher. 61 Rue des Saints-Pères, Paris. To Alphonse de Châteaubriant. Piriac-sur-Mer (Loire Inférieure), France. Expresses interest in publishing La brière. Is willing to send a contract based on the conditions set forth by Châteaubriant in an earlier letter. T.L., 1920 Jul 20; [2]. 27 cm.
    Removed from Châteaubriant, La brière. Paris: B. Grasset, 1923 (Lilly PQ2605 .H415 B85). 1980
  - Derème, Tristan, 1889-1941, poet. 19, Rue de la Pompe XVI. To Georges Ionescou. States he has received Ionscou's letter. Derème is sending him two pages of his manuscript to read. A.L.S., 1920 Oct 6; 1 p. 13.5 cm.; 2 p. 13.4 cm.
    In ink on blue paper.
    Enclosure of article "Oce et Negoce" dated Aug. 26, [19]20. A.D.S.
    Removed from Derème, Tristan, Le Zodiaque. Paris, Émile-Paul Frères, 1927 (Lilly PQ2607 .E56Z4). 1980
  - Barbusse, Henri, 1874-1935, author. Aumont par Senlia (Oise), France. To Henri Lenseigne. Speaks of the Flammarion edition of "Pleureuses", a copy of a poem from this work, and hopes that he is pleased with "ce petit hommage." T.L.S., 1920 Oct 20; 1 leaf 13 cm.
    Letterhead of Clarté, 12, rue Feydeau.
    Removed from Barbusse, Pleureuses, Paris, Bibliothèque-Charpentier, 1895 (PQ2603 .A56P7). 1974
  - Barbusse, Henri, 1874-1935, author. Geste. A.D.S., 1920 Oct.; 2 leaves 18 cm.
    Poem of five 4 line stanzas
    Appended note explains the relationship of the poem to the 1895 and Flammarion editions of Pleureses and hopes that Henri Lensigne, "bibliophile" is pleased with "ce modeste hommage."
    Bound in Barbusse, Pleureuses, Paris, Bibliothèque-Charpentier, 1895 (Lilly PQ2603 .A56P7). 1974
  - Barbusse, Henri, 1874-1935, author. Pleureuses: two verses. A.D.S., 1920, Oct.; 1 leaf 18 cm.
    Two verses from page 106 of the Charpentier edition of Pleureuses beginning "Comme un fleuve …" and "Je laisse sans penser…" in the volume inscribed to Henri Lenseigner.
  - Cocteau, Jean, 1889-1963, author. [Drawing of a sailor]. A.D.S., 1920?; 30.5x24.5 cm. 1 p.
    Inscribed: "a Maurice son ami."
    On title-page of Jean Cocteau, Escales. Paris: Editions de la sirène, 1920. (Lilly PQ2605.O15 E74). 1986
  - Boëx, Joseph Henri Honoré, 1856-1940, author. Paris. To Cher… ami. Offers comment on the life and work of the unidentifed recipient. A.L.S., 1921 Jun.; 1 p. 17 cm.
    Signed: J H Rosny aîné.
    In ink with penciled comment in margin.
    Removed from Rosny, Nell Horn de L'Armée du salut. Paris, E. Giraud et Cie, 1886 (Lilly 3-3907). 1978
  - Delteil, Joseph, 1894-1978, author. Paris. To Louis Brun. Paris. Encloses last chapter of his Cinq Sens. Would like to discuss the financial settlement. A.L.S., 1924 Feb. 27; 1 p. 9 cm.
    Written on postcard: Place de la Concorde, Concorde Square, Paris.
    Removed from Delteil, Allo! Paris!. Paris: Éditions des Quatres Chemins, 1926 (Lilly PQ2607 .E37 A75). 1980
  - Gourmont, Jean de, 1877-1928, critic. Paris 71 rue de St P… to Yves-Gérard le Dantec, 208 Boulevard Raspail, Paris XIV. Expresses concern about the reproduction of the portraits in "Muses." A.L.S., 1924 Dec 14; 1 p. 16.3 cm.
    Date from postmark.
    Written on fold-over note paper.
    Removed from Gourmont, Muses d'aujourd'hui. Paris, Mercure de France, 1910 (Lilly PQ443 .G6). 1985
  - [Papers concerning Le Bal du Comte d'Orgel by Raymond Radiguet.], 1924-1925; 6 holograph and printed pcs. 15.5-31.5 cm.; A.D. 4 p. 15.5 cm. n.d.
    Contents: 1-2). Le Bal, by Joseph Kessel. A.D.S. 3 p. 21 cm. n.d. Accompanied by the printed article as published in Figaro, 14 July 1924. 3). J[oseph] Kessel. Letter to Albert Pigasse, Paris. A.L.S. 1 p. 16 cm. 6 Mar. 1925. 4). Darius Milhaud. Letter to "cher ami". A.L.S. 1 p. 27.5 cm. n.d. 5). Corrected proof of unsigned leter to "Monsieur le Directeur du Temps." L. 1 p. 27 cm. 192-. 6). Holograph notes regarding the page proofs of Le Bal…, prepared by the firm of Martin Breslauer, from whom they were purchased.
    Removed from the page proofs of Radiguet, Le Bal du Comte d'Orgel. Paris, B. Grasset, 1924 (Lilly PQ2635 .A25B17). 1984
  - Léautaud, Paul, 1872-1956, editor, author. Mercure de France, 26, Rue de Conde, 26, Paris. To Monsieur. Concerns the problem of obtaining a place to live near his office. A.L.S., 1926 Feb 2; 1 p. 21 cm.
    Letter signed with the author's pseudonym of Maurice Boissard.
    Removed from Léautaud, Le petit ami … Paris Societe du Mercure de France, 1903 (Lilly PQ2623 E14P48). 1974
  - Auriol, Jean Georges Huyot, 1863-1938, novelist. 44 Rue De Abbesses, Paris, 18e. To Cher Ami. Complains that he missed the performance of Les Compères; expresses his love for Irish writers, James Stephens and Synge; Vers et Prose will reappear at Christmas; mentions meeting Valéry and concludes with a remark about Ernest Pascal. A.L.S., 1927 Feb 20; 4 p. 16 cm.
    The letter may be directed to Paul Fort.
    Stationery bears stylized initial in rust device.
  - Mortier, Alfred, 1865-1937, drama critic. Membre de L'association Professionelle de la Critique Dramatique & Musicale. 20, Rue du Printemps, XVIIe. To "chere Madame." Refers to La Jevne Parque by Paul Valéry. A. card S., 1928 Mar 24; 7 cm.
    Removed from Valéry, La Jevne Parque. Paris, Librairie Gallimard, 1936 (Lilly PQ2643 .A38J58 1936). 1974
  - Cocteau, Jean, 1889-1963, author. [Drawing with inscription to Jacques Marmel.] A.D.S., 1929?; 22x34 cm.
    Drawing in ink and red pencil.
    Inscription reads: "Souvenir de toute mon amitié à Jacques Marmel"
    On half-title page and verso of blank leaf preceding half-title page of Jean Cocteau, Les Enfants terribles: roman. [Paris]: Bernard Grasset, 1929. (Lilly PQ2605. O15 E56). 1986
  - Aveline, Claude, 1901-, author, publisher. L'Espézance, Font-Romeu (Pyr.-Orient.), France. To Charles Bosse. Concerns publishing background of André Gide's translation of William Blake's The marriage of heaven and hell. States that all but 43 of the 275 copies he published were destroyed. A.L.S., 1930 Feb 23; [4] p. 18 cm.
    Removed from William Blake, Le mariage du ciel et de l'enfer. Paris: C. Aveline, 1926 (Lilly PR4144 .M3214). 1981
  - Lyautey, Louis Hubert Gonzalve, 1854-1934, author, military officer. 5, Rue Bonaparte-VIe. To L. Bailly-Maitre. Is pleased to be remembered from Madagascar and thanks him for the Joan of Arc material. A.L.S., 1930 Mar 21; [2] p. 9 cm.
    Removed from André Maurois, Lyautey. Paris: Plon, 1931 (Lilly DC342.8 .L8 M25). 1981
  - Delteil, Joseph, 1894-1978, author. Pieusse (Aude), France. To "Mon cher ami." Will send his Don Juan "le ler Octobre – dans 8 jours!" and would like to know when it will be promoted. A.L.S., 1930 Sept. 23?; 1 p. 9 cm.
    Possibly to Louis Brun, editor at Grasset (Paris).
    On postcard: Vallée de l'Aude, Limoux, N.-D. de Marceille, La Vierge et l'Eglise.
    Removed from Delteil, Allo! Paris!. Paris: Éditions de Quatres Chemins, 1926 (Lilly PQ2607 .E37 A75). 1980
  - Barbusse, Henri, 1874-1935, author. Vigilia, Miramar par Théoule. To Octave Galhier. Barbusse will be happy to inscribe the writer's copy of Le Feu when he returns to Paris. A.L.S., 1931 Jan 15; 1 leaf 23 cm.
    Removed from Barbusse, Le Feu, Paris, Ernest Flammarion, 1916 (Lilly PQ2603 .A56F4 copy 1). 1974
  - Breton, Andre, 1896-1966, poet. Sans Connaissance [poem]., 1932 Mar 28; 4 p. 27 cm.
    Removed from Breton, Le Revolver a Cheveux Blancs, Paris, Editions des Cahiers Libres, 1932 (Lilly PQ2603.R35 R45) 1980
  - Régnier, Henri François Joseph de, 1864-1936, poet. To H. Camile Bizot, 19 Rue dela Mairie, Varader, Loire Inferieux. The poet inscribed the accompanying volume to the recipient with pleasure. A.L.S., 1933 Feb 26; 1 leaf 16 cm.
    Removed from Régnier, Sept Médailles amoureuses, Paris, La Centaine, 1928 (Lilly PQ2635 .E34S47) which is inscribed to "Camille Bizot." 1973
  - Jouhandeau, Marcel, 1888-1979, author. [Images de Paris; drafts of five word sketches.] A.D.S., 1934; [8] p. 20 cm.
    Inscribed by the author to "Mon cher Moré" on p. [1].
    Drafts mounted on stubs as follows: Gloire, 1 p., between p. 10-11; Ivrognesse, 1 p., between p. 12-13; La cravate de l'homme au sable, 1 p., between p. 22-23; Le corset, 2 p., between p. 80-81; L'homme qui se croyait Dieu-le-Père [published as "Dieu-le-Père"], 2 p., between p. 150-151 (Lilly PQ2619 .O76 I43)
    In Jouhandeau, Images de Paris, Paris: Gallimard, 1934. 1989
  - Picard, Gaston Louis Charles, 1892-, author. Paris, France. To Édouard Jean Marie Champion. Asking aid in securing the cross of a chevalier of the Legion of honor. A.L.S., 1935 July 1; 2 p. 20 cm.; 3 p. 31 cm.
    Accompanied by: 1) Gaston Louis Charles Picard to Édouard Jean Marie Champion, July 5, 1935. A.L.S. 3 p. 20 cm.; 2) France. Ministère de l'éducation Nationale to Édouard Jean Marie Champion, August 1, 1935. The Grand Chancellory has refused to award the cross of a chevalier of the Legion of honor to Gaston Picard. L.S. 1 p. 22 cm.; 3) Gaston Louis Charles Picard to Édouard Jean Marie Champion, August 9, 1935. Regrets at not having been given the cross of a chevalier of the Legion of honor. A.L.S. 2 p. 19 cm.; 4) Sketch of literary achievement of Gaston Louis Charles Picard. A.D.
    Removed from Gaston Louis Charles Picard's Hommage à Victor Hugo… Paris, La Caravelle, 1935 (PQ2298 .P5). 1951